Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1900s, 1900-1999; 11 boxes (10 partial)
  - Davies, Rhys: The skull, 1936; 38941; portion of 1 box
    Author: Davies, Rhys
    Bifolium, 4to; 3 wood engravings by Sylvia Marshall; previous fold, mostly fine. Prospectus for a short story by Davies to be published in an edition of 110 copies. Specimen pages provided. 2 other titles from the Press mentioned on the back page.
  - Van Gogh, Vincent: Letters to an artist...to Anton Ridder van Rappard, 1881-1885. With an introduction by Walter Pach, 1936; 39016; portion of 1 box
    Author: Van Gogh, Vincent
    New York: Viking Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrations, printed in blue and black; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for the publications of a stash of newly discovered illustrated letters by the artist. Printed in 2 editions, one of which is limited to 650 copies.
  - Church, Peggy Pond: Familiar journey, 1936; 39148; portion of 1 box
    Author: Church, Peggy Pond
    Santa Fe: Writers' Editions
    Bifolium, 12mo; fine. Prospectus for a collection of poems in an edition designed and printed at the Rydal Press; limited to 430 copies.
  - Webb books 1937, 39038; portion of 1 box
    St. Paul: Webb Book Publishing Co.
    12mo, unpaginated; original green printed wrappers (soiling); fine. Titles from the press include James M. Drew's course "Blacksmithing"; Maurice H. Decker's "Practical Home Tanning and Fur Dressing"; H.M. Lamon and J. W. Kinghorne's "Practical Poultry Production"; C.S. Plumb's "A study of Farm Animals"; and A.D. Wilson and C.W. Warburton's "Field Crops". Integral order form printed on inside of back wrapper.
  - Storm, Marian: The life of Saint Rose. First American saint and only American woman saint, 1937; 39147; portion of 1 box
    Author: Storm, Marian
    Bifolium, 8vo; a bit worn from handling, else fine. Prospectus for a history of the Peruvian saint Rose of Lima, also known for being the first saint born in the New World. Edition limited to 430 copies.
  - Fechin, Alexandra: March of the past, 1937; 39146; portion of 1 box
    Author: Fechin, Alexandra
    Santa Fe: Writers' Editions.
    Bifolium, top left-hand corner creased, else fine. Prospectus for a work comprised of 2 stories on the Russian revolution published in an edition limited to 500 signed copies.
  - Walpole, Horace: The Yale edition of Horace Walpole's correspondence. Editor: Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis, 1937; 39401; portion of 1 box
    Author: Walpole, Horace
    8vo, unpaginated; plate; original blue pictorial wrappers, toned, edges chipped and worn, spine starting to split; title page detached. Provides specimen pages and plate.
  - Cary, Melbert B., Jr.: A bibliography of the Village Press...with an account of the genesis of the Press by Frederic W. Goudy and a part of the diary for 1903 of Will Ransom, its co-founder, 1938; 39129; portion of 1 box
    Author: Cary, Melbert B., Jr.
    Bifolium, 8vo; fine. Prospectus for a work "issued to celebrate the 35th anniversary of the founding of the oldest private printing office in America," illustrated in collotype by Goudy, husband and wife, in an edition of 250 copies. 2 specimen pages provided.
  - Collectors' items. Books selected from the publications of the Yale University Press and of interest to collectors because of their contents or formats, 1938; 39159; portion of 1 box
    New Haven: Yale University Press.
    8vo, pp. 14; original brown printed wrappers; fine. Titles devided into 5 sections and include "The Letters of Charles and Mary Lamb"; Paul Claudel's "The Book of Christopher Colubmus"; Robert W. Neeser's "American Naval Songs and Balloads"; St. John de Crèvecoeur's "Sketches of Eighteenth Century America"; Edward Deming Andrews and Faith Andrews' "Shaker Furniture. The craftsmanship of an American communal sect"; Gisela M.A. Richter's "Red-figured Athenian Vases in the Metropolitan Museum of Art"; Hiram Bingham's "The Exploration and Excavation of Machu Picchu"; R. Selden Rose's "Wine Making for the Amateur"; and Jean Ribaut's "The True Relation of the Discovery of Terra Florida. A facsimile reprint".
  - A miscellany comprising those books from this Press that may be had by the public and of which copies remain at the time of printing, 1939; 39127; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; woodcut title page vignette printed in pink, fore-edge tipped in purple; fine. Titles include "The Terms of the Armistice, fourth Armstice Day issue" in sheet aluminum binding; and "Treasure in the Forest: Wells," with colored stencils by W.A. Dwiggins.
  - Delightes for ladies to adorne their persons, tables, closets, and distillatories with beavties, banqvets, perfumes & waters. Reade, practice, & censure, 1939; 39374; portion of 1 box
    Herrin, Illinois: Trovillion Private Press
    Bifolium, 16mo; facsimile title page, text printed in brown and black; fine. Prospectus for a reprint of the original 1609 edition on female cosmetics, "England's first practical treatise on cooking and beauty culture". Integral order form and list of "other similar books" printed on back.
  - Delightes for ladies to adorne their persons, tables, closets, and distillatories with beavties, banqvets, perfumes & waters. Reade, practice, & censure, 1939; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 16mo; facsimile title page, text printed in orange and black; fine. Prospectus for a reprint of the original 1609 edition on female cosmetics, "England's first practical treatise on cooking and beauty culture". Integral order form and list of "other similar books" printed on back.
  - Melville, Herman: The encantadas. Or, enchanted isles...With an introduction, critical epilogue & bibliographical notes by Victor Wolfgang von Hagen, 1940; 39034; portion of 1 box
    Burlingame, California: William P. Wreden
    Bifolium, 4to; text printed in brown and black; mostly fine. Prospectus for a limited edition of 550 copies; order form laid in.
    Filed under Wreden.
  - Goudy, Frederic W.: Typologia: Studies in type design and type making, 1940; 36597; portion of 1 box
    Berkeley: University of California Press
    Bifolium, large 8vo; prospectus illustrated with photograph of Goudy ("One of the greatest typographic figures of any year, of any age") at a matrix-engraving machine. Integral address and order form on back page. Order form addressed to Philip C. Duschnes of New York. Previous folds, text in red and black.
  - Dwiggins, W.A.: A technique for dealing with artists, 1941; 39130; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (83 x 140 mm.); fine. Postcard prospectus for a booklet that "really bridges the gulf between Artist and Business Man" which Dwiggins originally compiled for personal use and to educate his clients.
  - Ths is the army, 1942; 37466; portion of 1 box
    New York: This is the Army, Inc.
    3 leaves, TLs to Emerson G. Wulling from Col. Chas. F.H. Johnson on company letterhead, 4to; announcing the publication of a work published in order to raise moeny for the Army Emergency Relief Fund, in a limited edition, each copy inscribed by Irving Berlin; introduction by Maxwell Anderson and with contributions by Alexander Woollcott and Hendrik Van Loon, among others. Foxing, previous folds.
  - Albright, Rachel: Poems of the middle west, 1942; 39716; portion of 1 box
    Author: Albright, Rachel
    Cedar Rapids, Iowa: Torch Press.
    Bifolium, 8vo; author photograph; previous folds, fore-edge toned and chipped. Provides sample poems, press reviews, and an integral order form.
  - Catalogue of the library of Thomas Jefferson 1815, 1943; 36388; portion of 1 box
    Washington: United States Government Printing Office
    Large 8vo, pp. 17, [1], black and white facsimiles; prospectus for the library that would become the foundation for the Library of Congress.
  - Mason, Henry L.: Hymn-tunes of Lowell Mason. A bibliography, 1944; 39011; portion of 1 box
    Author: Mason, Henry L.
    Cambridge, Mass.: University Press
    8vo, unpaginated; pictorial self wrappers, blue decorative borders; fine. Prospectus for the bibliography of "The Father of Protestant Church Music in America".
  - Charter of the United Nations and statute of the International Court of Justice, together with interim arrangements concluded by the governments represented at the United Nations conference on international organization: facsimile edition, 1945; 42463; portion of 1 box
    Berkeley: University of California Press.
    Bifolium, large 4to; facsimiles; previous fold, some soiling; distributor Philip C. Duschnes's rubber stamp on front panel; good over all. Advertisement announcing that "This edition of the United Nations Charter and the accompanying documents is an exact facsimile of the volumes which were officially signed by the delegates of the United Nations Conference on International Organization at San Francisco on June 26, 1945". Prospectus provides sample pages in actual and reduced size.
  - Mertins, Louis and Esther: The intervals of Robert Frost. A critical bibliography by Louis and Esther Mertins. With an introduction by Fulmer Mood, 1947; 36595; portion of 1 box
    Author: Mertins, Louis and Esther
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for this bibliography, which includes facsimile of a poem in Frost's hand; and an integral order form at bottom of back page. Text in red and black. Previous folds.
  - Bell, H. Idris and C.H. Roberts: A descriptive catalogue of the Greek papyri in the collection of Wilfred Merton...Volume I. With fifty-one plates, 1948; 39048; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bell, H. Idris and C.H. Roberts
    London: Emery Walker Limited
    Bifolium, 4to; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for a catalogue of the "fifty best" papyri items collected by Wilfred Merton between 1924 and 1926 with collotype facsimiles for each text. Two specimen pages provided
  - The new colophon. A book collectors' quarterly, 1948; 36367; portion of 1 box
    New York: Zeitlin et VerBrugge
    Bifolium, 4to, text in black and orange; prospectus for the resuscitation of the Colophon "By the same staff--in the same spirit," giving the names of the editors and contributing editors, including W.A. Dwiggins and Alfred A. Knopf. Back leaf provides information on the format, advertising, and subscription prices. Order form loosely inserted. Previous fold.
  - Arberry, A.J., trans.: The Ruba'iyat of Jalal Al-Din Rumi. Select translations into English verse, 1949; 39050; portion of 1 box
    Author: Arberry, A.J., trans.
    London: Emery Walker
    Bifolium, 4to; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for an English translation of a newly-discovered manuscript in the collection of Chester Beatty, originally containing nearly 2,000 quatrains, but here pared down to 360. Edition to be limited to 500 copies. 2 specimen pages provided.
  - Arberry, A.J., ed.: The Ruba'iyat of Omar Khayyam edited from a newly discovered manuscript dated 658 (1259-60) in the possession of A. Chester Beatty...with comparative English versions by Edward Fitzgerald, E.H. Whinefield, and the editor, 1949; 39049; portion of 1 box
    Author: Arberry, A.J., ed.
    Bifolium, 4to; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for an edition limited to 500 copies in hand-made paper. 2 specimen pages provided.
  - Rollins, Carl Purington: Off the dead bank. Addresses, reviews, and verses, 1949; 38995; portion of 1 box
    Author: Rollins, Carl Purington
    New York: Typophiles
    Bifolium, 12mo; decorative borders; previous fold, else fine. Provides specimen page from a work compiled from 4 decades of output by the author. Published in an edition limited to 300 copies and printed at the Yale University Press.
  - Bean, Walton: Boss Ruef's San Francisco: The story of the Union Labor Party, big business, and the graft prosecution, 1952; 36602; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bean, Walton
    Broadside, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for the "dramatic story of political graft, of the man who symbolized it, and of the newspaper man who exposed him". Integral order form at bottom of sheet, photographic illustration on verso. Previous folds.
  - Arrighi: The first writing book. An English translation and facsimile text of...Operina, the first manual of the Chancery hand, with introduction and notes by John Howard Benson, 1954; portion of 1 box
    Author: Arrighi
    Bifolium, 8vo; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for an English translation of a text originally printed in Rome in 1522, and the second in the series Studies in the History of Calligraphy, sponsored by Harvard College Library and the Newberry Library. Price written in manuscript in green pen. Typewritten card dated 10/9/54 laid in Inclues price and where to send orders.
  - Arrighi: The first writing book. An English translation and facsimile text of...Operina, the first manual of the Chancery hand, with introduction and notes by John Howard Benson, 1954; 39149; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for an English translation of a text originally printed in Rome in 1522, and the second in the series Studies in the History of Calligraphy, sponsored by Harvard College Library and the Newberry Library. Price written in manuscript in green pen. Order form addressed to the distributor, the Chiswick Book Shop, New York, laid in.
  - Blake, William: Songs of innocence and of experience, 1955; 38972; portion of 1 box
    London: Trianon Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; text printed in brown; fine. Prospectus for a facsimile edition of Blake's illuminated poem, published for the William Blake Trust and distributed in the United States by Philip C. Duschnes. Specimen page, order form, and envelope laid in.
  - Blanck, Jacob: Bibliography of American literature. Volume I, 1955; 39151; portion of 1 box
    Author: Blanck, Jacob
    Broadside, 16mo (139 mm.); printed in blue; fine. Prospectus for the first volume of the BAL, covering Henry Adams to Donn Byrne.
  - Joyce, James: Letters...Volumes II and III. Edited 1966 by Richard Ellman, 39013; portion of 1 box
    Author: Joyce, James
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 8vo; black and white photographic illustrations and facsimiles; edges a bit bumped, else fine. Integral order form addressed to the Gotham Book Mart, New York.
  - Hazen, Allen T.: A catalogue of Horace Walpole's library...with "Horace Walpole's Library" by Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis, 1969; 39160; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hazen, Allen T.
    Bifolium, 4to; 2 black and white illustrations; previous folds, corners a bit creased, else fine. Prospectus for the 3-volume catalogue; specimen page provided; list of the 34 projected volumes of the Walpole correspondence to be complete in 1975 printed on back. Photocopy of an newspaper clipping from the New York Herald Tribune Books, Sunday, January 1, 1933, laid in.
  - Kelley, Robert E. and O.M. Brack, Jr.: Samuel Johnson's early biographers, 1970; 42488; portion of 1 box
    Author: Kelley, Robert E. and O.M. Brack, Jr.
    Iowa City: University of Iowa Press.
    Single sheet folded into 8- (now 6-) sided pamphlet; illustration, printed on stiff tan paper; near fine. Prospectus for a study on seven Johnson biographers with a list of additional books of interest provided. Integral order form has been neatly removed.
  - Mueller, Lisel, John Knoepfle, and Dave Etter: Voyages to the inland sea. Essays and poems, 1971; 39123; portion of 1 box
    Author: Mueller, Lisel, John Knoepfle, and Dave Etter
    La Crosse: Wisconsin State University
    Broadside, small folio (280 mm.); illustration printed in grey; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for a collection of pieces published jointly with the Center for Contemporary Poetry, the Murphy Library, and the English Department at the University. "The first volume in a projected series on contemporary midwestern poetry". Edition limited to 500 copies.
  - Pollack, Felix, James Hearst, and John Woods: Voyages to the inland sea, II. Essays and poems, 1972; 39124; portion of 1 box
    Author: Pollack, Felix, James Hearst, and John Woods
    La Crosse: University of Wisconsin
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustration printed in pink; fine. Prospectus for the second volume in a series of midwestern poetry, edited by John Judson.
  - Seventhall, R.E., Thomas McGrath, and Robert Dana: Voyages to the inland sea, 3. Essays and poems, 1973; 39125; portion of 1 box
    Author: Seventhall, R.E., Thomas McGrath, and Robert Dana
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustration printed in mauve; fine. Prospectus for the third volume in a series of midwestern poetry, published in an edition of 400 copies. Specimen page provide; integral order form.
  - The Veritas missal for Sundays and principal feasts with the new official liturgical texts of the readings and prayers, 1973; 39008; portion of 1 box
    Dublin: Veritas Publications
    12mo, pp. [4]; self-wrappers, printed in brown and black; fine. 4 specimen pages provided. Published for the Talbot Press Liturgical Books.
  - Greenberg, Alvin, George Chambers, and Raymond Roseliep: Voyages to the inland sea, IV. Essays and poems, 1974; 39126; portion of 1 box
    Author: Greenberg, Alvin, George Chambers, and Raymond Roseliep
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustration printed in yellow; fine. Prospectus for the fourth volume in a series of midwestern poetry, published in an edition of 500 copies. Excerpt from the introduction by John Judson printed on back.
  - Heathorn, R.J.: Learn the book, 1975; 42471; portion of 1 box
    Author: Heathorn, R.J.
    Wayzgoosers.
    Bifolium, 12mo; printed in red and black; fine. "A magical learning machine using free brain power now ready" - heading title. Prospectus consisting of an excerpt from Heathorn's piece, originally published in "Punch" in 1962.
  - Limited editions of books & prints, 1975-6, 39117; portion of 1 box
    Cheltenham, Glos.: Whittington Press
    4to, pp. 8; black and white illustrations throughout; original orange pictorial wrappers printed in red and black; fine. Titles include Lewis Carroll's "The Hunting of the Snark"; and an edition of four hand-colored lithographs of Virginia Woolf by Richard Kennedy. Order form laid in.
  - Albers, Josef: Homage to the square, 1976; 37022; portion of 1 box
    Author: Albers, Josef
    Beford Village, New York: Tyler Graphics Ltd
    Bifolium, 4to; hand printed screen miniature of the artist's last print, Homage to the Square, "commemorating his 88th birthday".
  - Albers, Josef: Never before, 1976; 37018; portion of 1 box
    Beford Village, New York: Tyler Graphics Ltd.
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for this "portfolio of twelve original five-color screen prints"; includes a miniature specimen print.
  - A little rebellion now & then. Sixteen of America's finest typographers-printers and an Englishman, print on the American Revolution, 1976; 39031; portion of 1 box
    Santa Cruz, California: William James Association
    Bifolium, 4to; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for a series of Revolutionary Broadsides in an edition of 200 copies.
  - Levine, Philip: The names of the lost, 1976; 39089; portion of 1 box
    Iowa City: Windhover Press.
    Broadside, 16mo (153 mm.); text printed in red and black; fine. Postcard prospectus for a poetry collection published in a signed limited edition of 200 copies.
  - Books to be printed & published...during 1977, 39116; portion of 1 box
    Cheltenham, Gloucestershire: Whittington Press
    12mo, pp. 15; illustrations, many photographic, throughout; white photographic self wrappers; fine. Titles from the Press include "The Song of Songs"; and "Marlborough, town and countryside". Also includes list of titles still available and integral order form.
  - Robbins, Rae Gallant: The Bloomsbury group: a selective bibliography, 1978; 42477; portion of 1 box
    Author: Robbins, Rae Gallant
    Portland: Walking Dream Books.
    Bifolium, large 4to; printed on blue paper; fine. Prospectus for the "First bibliography to gather together the members of the Bloomsbury group as an intellectual force". Integral order form provided.
  - Wells, Dean F.: The ghosts of Rowan Oak: William Faulkner's ghost stories for children, 1980; 41000; portion of 1 box
    Author: Wells, Dean F.
    Oxford, MS: Yoknapatawpha Press.
    8vo, pp. 8; black and white illustrations; pictorial self wrappers, general light shelf wear, occasional ink check marks in margins, else a good copy. Publisher's catalogue featuring Wells's account of the ghost stories her uncle, William Faulkner, would tell when she was a child. Blank order form printed inside back wrapper.
  - TWB books mail-order customer price list, 1981; 38915; portion of 1 box
    Woolwich, Maine: TBW Books
    Broadside, oblong 8vo (161 mm.216 mm.); fine. List of titles from the book club with the photocopy of a TLs from Thea Wheelwright. In original envelope.
  - Fall 1981. The Toothpaste Press catalog, 38962; portion of 1 box
    West Branch, Iowa: Toothpaste Press
    Oblong 12mo, unpaginated; black and white illustrations throughout; original blue printed wrappers, fine.
  - Kicknosway, Faye: Asparagus, asparagus, ah sweet asparagus, 1981; 39245; portion of 1 box
    Author: Kicknosway, Faye
    West Branch, Iowa: Toothpaste Press.
    Broadside, oblong 8vo (141 x 202 mm.); illustration printed in green; fine. Prospectus for a collection of poetry, illustrated by the author and published in an edition limited to 1200 copies.
  - The Toothpaste Press books in print 1982, 38963; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; 2 black and white illustrations, printed on peach paper; previous folds, else fine.
  - Stella, Frank: Swan engravings, 1982; 37021; portion of 1 box
    Author: Stella, Frank
    Bedford Village, New York: Tyler Graphics Ltd.
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for "A series of black and white etchings on TGL handmade paper"; miniature reproduction of one of the etchings tipped in. "This brochure was printed in an edition of 4000 copies." Text in red and black.
  - Motherwell, Robert: Lament for Lorca, 1982; 37020; portion of 1 box
    Author: Motherwell, Robert
    Bifolium, oblong 4to; prospectus for handprinted lithograph in an edition limited to 52 copies; miniature of the image tipped in. "This brochure was printed in an edition of 3000 copies." Text in brown and black.
  - Werner, Arno: One man's work. Introduced and edited by Carol J. Blinn, 1982; 39063; portion of 1 box
    Author: Werner, Arno
    Easthampton: Warwick Press
    Bifolium, small 8vo; color illustration; fine. Prospectus for an edition of a speech on bookbinding delivered by Werner at the Houghton Library in 1981. Designed and printed letterpress by Blinn in a limited edition of 200 copies.
  - [List of titles], 1983; 38964; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; previous folds, else fine. Titles available from the Press in the fall of 1983.
  - Winter 1983 titles, 38961; portion of 1 box
    St. Paul, MN: Toothpaste Press
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, small 4to; blue tipped edge; fine. Titles include "Singularities: A science fiction story series" and Thomas M. Disch's "Ringtime". Order form and discount announcement from the distributor Bookslinger laid in.
  - Books...1983 & 1984, portion of 1 box
    Small 8vo, pp. 15; black and white illustrations throughout; original tan pictorial wrappers, text printed in brown; fine. Titles from the catalogue include "Matrix 3," and "The Mirror and the Eye: fifty Sufi Rubaiyat by Omar Khayyam". Integral order form. Some of the books are crossed out and labelled O.P.
  - Books...1983 & 1984, 39110; portion of 1 box